Hello everyone, the title of my presentation is "Generating the Cloud Motion Winds Field from Satellite Cloud Imagery Using Deep Learning Approach".
My name is Chao Tan, from Chongqing University of Technology.
Cloud motion winds field is derived from geostationary satellite-observed motions of clouds features.
The algorithm estimates the average motion vectors of the atmosphere in a certain area based on the movement of the same cloud mass in two consecutive infrared satellite cloud imageries.
Cloud motion winds field have been shown to provide reasonable estimates of the ambient tropospheric wind, and its application is wide ranging.
It contributes to forecast diagnostics of weather conditions, as well as numerical weather prediction.
In addition, cloud motion winds field can also provide basic guidance for such field as ultraviolet index and solar energy prediction.
With the application of image processing and machine learning technology in various fields,
we noticed that the cloud motion wind algorithm is similar to the task of optical flow estimation in computer vision.
Therefore, we formalized the cloud motion wind estimation task as the problem of unsupervised dense optical flow prediction.
Unlike traditional image processing methods, we use deep learning methods to learn the feature representation automatically,
and it also greatly improve the calculation speed and efficiency of the algorithm.
It is worth noting that duo to the uncertainty of atmospheric movement,
the brightness consistency between two adjacent satellite cloud imageries is not guaranteed,
so the unsupervised optic flow estimation based on photometric consistency is not suitable for use.
In addition, cloud motion winds estimation often requires more robust performance than optical flow prediction,
and a large-scale dataset is also required for training the deep learning models.
In order to train our deep learning model, we first propose a brand-new large-scale cloud motion winds dataset named CMWD,
which contains more than 6300 training samples and 700 testing samples.
Each sample consists of two geostationary satellite cloud imageries, taken a one-hour intervals over a vast of the Pacific Northwest.
In order to visualize the output optical flow, we encode the generated two-dimensional flow field with color in the HSV color model.
During the training phase, we use PCA-Flow to generate it as the supervision for the model.
In addition, we also convert the generated vector field into two visualization products, one is the common dense vector arrow diagram.
The other is the flux streamline diagram, which can continuously display the direction and intensity of the wind field.
We use FlowNet-S as a reference network and this architecture consists of a contractive part followed by an expanding part.
The contractive part takes as input two infrared cloud imageries stacked together, and processes them with a cascade of stride deconvolution layers.
The expanding part implements a "skip layer" architecture
that combines information from various levels of contractive part with "up convolving" layers to iteratively refine the coarse cloud motion winds filed predictions.
In addition, we use endpoint error (EPE) during the training process, and we use several intermediate losses placed at various stages of the expansionary part.
The intermediate losses are meant to guide earlier layers more directly towards the final objective.
We first use the paired infrared satellite cloud imagery on CMWD dataset to conduct the experiment.
It can be seen from the experimental results that our model can well estimate the upper-air wind motion at its location,
whether it is a large air mass movement or a small-to-medium-scale anticyclonic spiral movement.
We also try to use single infrared cloud imagery to estimate the cloud motion winds field, which is not feasible for conventional methods.
However, because deep neural network can learn from a large amount of data,
many basic patterns of atmospheric motion can be detected by the model, and then predict through the state of the whole cloud system.
From the experimental results, it can be seen that even with only one input image,
our model is still able to make a rough estimate of cloud motion winds field under the current situation.
Meanwhile, our model can separate different cloud structures in cloud imagery and make different estimates accordingly.
Here are the dynamic image samples with paired and single cloud imagery superimposed on flux streamline diagram,
from which we can intuitively see the effectiveness of our proposed method.
In this work, we propose to use a deep convolutional neural network to estimate the cloud motion winds field.
Meanwhile, we also present a large-scale cloud motion winds dataset for deep learning research.
The experimental results illustrate the efficient performance of our model, and it can also handle the case without paired satellite cloud imagery input.
That's all. Thank you.